{
  "chapters": [
    {
      "chapter_number": 1,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 1,
          "question": "What color is Bilbo's front door into his hobbit hole?",
          "options": [
            "Yellow",
            "Blue",
            "Green",
            "Brown"
          ],
          "answer": "Green"
        },
        {
          "number": 2,
          "question": "Who is the first dwarf to arrive at Bilbo's house in Chapter 1?",
          "options": [
            "Balin",
            "Bombur",
            "Gloin",
            "Dwalin"
          ],
          "answer": "Dwalin"
        },
        {
          "number": 3,
          "question": "What does Gloin say about Bilbo that enrages Bilbo so much that he overcomes his fears and joins the adventurers?",
          "options": [
            "As fierce as a dragon in a pinch",
            "Our friend and fellow conspirator",
            "Little fellow bobbing on the mat",
            "More like a grocer than a burglar"
          ],
          "answer": "Little fellow bobbing on the mat"
        },
        {
          "number": 4,
          "question": "Who made the map that Gandalf gives to Thorin?",
          "options": [
            "Dain",
            "Thrain",
            "Thror",
            "The Necromancer"
          ],
          "answer": "Thror"
        },
        {
          "number": 5,
          "question": "What was the name of the town of Men that was under the shadow of the Lonely Mountain until the dragon came and destroyed it?",
          "options": [
            "Esgaroth",
            "Moria",
            "Bywater",
            "Dale"
          ],
          "answer": "Dale"
        },
        {
          "number": 6,
          "question": "Which dwarf has a smoke-ring blowing competition or game with Gandalf?",
          "options": [
            "Thorin",
            "Bifur",
            "Balin",
            "Gloin"
          ],
          "answer": "Thorin"
        },
        {
          "number": 7,
          "question": "What musical instrument does Thorin Oakenshield play?",
          "options": [
            "A fiddle",
            "A flute",
            "A harp",
            "A clarinet"
          ],
          "answer": "A harp"
        },
        {
          "number": 8,
          "question": "What color is Thorin's hood?",
          "options": [
            "Scarlet",
            "Sky blue",
            "Green",
            "Yellow and orange"
          ],
          "answer": "Sky blue"
        },
        {
          "number": 9,
          "question": "What game or sport was accidentally invented by Bilbo's ancestor Bullroarer Took?",
          "options": [
            "Football",
            "Snooker",
            "Golf",
            "Polo"
          ],
          "answer": "Golf"
        },
        {
          "number": 10,
          "question": "Which pair of dwarves are the youngest?",
          "options": [
            "Balin and Dwalin",
            "Dori and Nori",
            "Fili and Kili",
            "Oin and Gloin"
          ],
          "answer": "Fili and Kili"
        },
        {
          "number": 11,
          "question": "What was the name of Bilbo's mother?",
          "options": [
            "Lobelia Sackville-Baggins",
            "Belladonna Took",
            "Rosemary Took",
            "Bluebell Belladonna"
          ],
          "answer": "Belladonna Took"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "chapter_number": 2,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 12,
          "question": "What sort of drink does Gandalf ask Bilbo to get him in Chapter 1?",
          "options": [
            "Coffee",
            "Beer",
            "Red wine",
            "Porter"
          ],
          "answer": "Red wine"
        },
        {
          "number": 13,
          "question": "What is the name of the inn where the dwarves meet Bilbo in Chapter 2?",
          "options": [
            "The Prancing Pony",
            "The Golden Perch",
            "The Green Dragon",
            "The Bridge and Bottle"
          ],
          "answer": "The Green Dragon"
        },
        {
          "number": 14,
          "question": "Whose hood and cloak does Bilbo borrow?",
          "options": [
            "Gloin's",
            "Thorin's",
            "Dwalin's",
            "Gandalf's"
          ],
          "answer": "Dwalin's"
        },
        {
          "number": 15,
          "question": "Which dwarves are the best at lighting fires?",
          "options": [
            "Bifur and Bofur",
            "Kili and Fili",
            "Nori and Ori",
            "Oin and Gloin"
          ],
          "answer": "Oin and Gloin"
        },
        {
          "number": 16,
          "question": "Which of the following is not a name for the trolls?",
          "options": [
            "Sam",
            "William",
            "Bert",
            "Tom"
          ],
          "answer": "Sam"
        },
        {
          "number": 17,
          "question": "What does Bilbo try to steal from the trolls?",
          "options": [
            "A pony",
            "A purse",
            "A jug of beer",
            "A dagger"
          ],
          "answer": "A purse"
        },
        {
          "number": 18,
          "question": "Which troll catches Bilbo in Chapter 2?",
          "options": [
            "William",
            "All three of them",
            "Tom",
            "Bert"
          ],
          "answer": "William"
        },
        {
          "number": 19,
          "question": "Which dwarf puts up the most fight when the trolls try to capture him?",
          "options": [
            "Thorin",
            "Gloin",
            "Bombur",
            "Balin"
          ],
          "answer": "Thorin"
        },
        {
          "number": 20,
          "question": "What does Thorin use as a weapon against the trolls in Chapter 2?",
          "options": [
            "A branch torn off a tree",
            "A burning branch from the fire",
            "A cauldron of boiling water",
            "A dagger"
          ],
          "answer": "A burning branch from the fire"
        },
        {
          "number": 21,
          "question": "What cooking method do the trolls decide on first of all before Gandalf stirs up the argument again?",
          "options": [
            "Sitting on them and squashing them",
            "Mincing them and making them into pies",
            "Mincing them and boiling them",
            "Roasting the dwarves slowly"
          ],
          "answer": "Roasting the dwarves slowly"
        },
        {
          "number": 22,
          "question": "What does Bilbo take from the trolls' hoard of loot?",
          "options": [
            "A large, clumsy key",
            "A pot full of gold coins",
            "A long beautiful sword in a jewelled scabbard",
            "A knife big enough to serve him as a short sword"
          ],
          "answer": "A knife big enough to serve him as a short sword"
        },
        {
          "number": 23,
          "question": "What foodstuffs do the adventurers take from the troll's cave for breakfast?",
          "options": [
            "Cheese, eggs, sausages, and tomatoes",
            "Mutton bones, mince pies and sausages",
            "Ale, bread, cheese and bacon",
            "Bacon, beer, rabbit pie, and apples"
          ],
          "answer": "Ale, bread, cheese and bacon"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "chapter_number": 3,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 24,
          "question": "Where does Bilbo hide while the trolls are fighting and arguing?",
          "options": [
            "In a tree trunk",
            "In the trolls' cave",
            "In a bush",
            "Under a sack"
          ],
          "answer": "In a bush"
        },
        {
          "number": 25,
          "question": "What is the other name for Rivendell?",
          "options": [
            "The Last Homely House",
            "The Hidden Valley",
            "The Edge of the Wild",
            "The Valley of the Elves"
          ],
          "answer": "The Last Homely House"
        },
        {
          "number": 26,
          "question": "What is unusual or rare about Elrond's ancestry?",
          "options": [
            "He is half elf and half human",
            "He is half elf and half goblin",
            "He is half human and half hobbit",
            "He is half human and half goblin"
          ],
          "answer": "He is half elf and half human"
        },
        {
          "number": 27,
          "question": "On what day does Elrond read the runes on the swords and on the map?",
          "options": [
            "Midsummer morning",
            "Bilbo's birthday",
            "Midsummer's Eve",
            "The autumn equinox"
          ],
          "answer": "Midsummer's Eve"
        },
        {
          "number": 28,
          "question": "What is the English translation for the names of the swords (Orcrist and Glamdring) that Thorin and Gandalf now own?",
          "options": [
            "Tailbiter and Flame of the West",
            "Goblin-cleaver and Foe-hammer",
            "Truefriend and Goblin-hammer",
            "Warhammer and Dragonslayer"
          ],
          "answer": "Goblin-cleaver and Foe-hammer"
        },
        {
          "number": 29,
          "question": "What is another name for the Dwarves' New Year?",
          "options": [
            "The Threshold of Winter",
            "The Hunter's Moon",
            "Durin's Day",
            "The Day of the Thrush"
          ],
          "answer": "Durin's Day"
        },
        {
          "number": 30,
          "question": "What phase of the moon is showing when Elrond studies the map?",
          "options": [
            "A full moon",
            "A gibbous moon",
            "A new moon",
            "A crescent moon"
          ],
          "answer": "A crescent moon"
        },
        {
          "number": 31,
          "question": "Where were Glamdring and Orcrist originally forged?",
          "options": [
            "In Rivendell itself",
            "In Thror's kingdom that was destroyed by the dragon",
            "In the ancient elvish kingdom of Gondolin",
            "In the Mines of Moria"
          ],
          "answer": "In the ancient elvish kingdom of Gondolin"
        },
        {
          "number": 32,
          "question": "What does Elrond dislike about dwarves?",
          "options": [
            "Their cruelty and wickedness towards dragons",
            "Their singing",
            "Their long beards",
            "Their love of gold"
          ],
          "answer": "Their love of gold"
        },
        {
          "number": 33,
          "question": "Where are the elves hiding when they sing nonsense songs to welcome the adventurers to Rivendell?",
          "options": [
            "On the roof of Rivendell",
            "In trees beside the path",
            "Beside the stream",
            "Under the narrow stone bridge"
          ],
          "answer": "In trees beside the path"
        },
        {
          "number": 34,
          "question": "What does Bilbo's handwriting look like?",
          "options": [
            "Crabbed and rather clumsy",
            "Thin and spidery",
            "Flowing and beautiful",
            "Cunning and cryptic"
          ],
          "answer": "Thin and spidery"
        },
        {
          "number": 35,
          "question": "Which of the following is not a hazard that needs to be avoided in the path leading to Rivendell?",
          "options": [
            "Deceptively green bogs",
            "A very narrow bridge over a swift-flowing stream",
            "Steep slopes and deep ravines",
            "Avalanches and rock falls"
          ],
          "answer": "Avalanches and rock falls"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "chapter_number": 4,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 36,
          "question": "What type of bird is named in the moon-letters on the map?",
          "options": [
            "An eagle",
            "A sparrow",
            "A thrush",
            "A raven"
          ],
          "answer": "A thrush"
        },
        {
          "number": 37,
          "question": "What weather forces the adventurers to seek shelter in a cave in Chapter 4?",
          "options": [
            "A blizzard",
            "A hurricane",
            "A thunderstorm",
            "Hail and sleet"
          ],
          "answer": "A thunderstorm"
        },
        {
          "number": 38,
          "question": "Who found the cave in Chapter 4?",
          "options": [
            "Bifur, Bofur and Bombur",
            "Gandalf and Bilbo",
            "Balin and Dwalin",
            "Fili and Kili"
          ],
          "answer": "Fili and Kili"
        },
        {
          "number": 39,
          "question": "How many goblins grab Bilbo?",
          "options": [
            "Six",
            "Two",
            "None - Bilbo escapes",
            "Thirty"
          ],
          "answer": "Two"
        },
        {
          "number": 40,
          "question": "What do the goblins use to beat time while they sing?",
          "options": [
            "Hammers and tongs",
            "Footsteps and whips",
            "Cymbals and tamborines",
            "Drums and gongs"
          ],
          "answer": "Footsteps and whips"
        },
        {
          "number": 41,
          "question": "What was the final fate of the ponies?",
          "options": [
            "The goblins used them to draw carts in the mines",
            "The goblins ate them",
            "They starved to death",
            "They escaped back to Rivendell"
          ],
          "answer": "The goblins ate them"
        },
        {
          "number": 42,
          "question": "Which of the following devices do the goblins not make (or have made for them)?",
          "options": [
            "Instruments of torture",
            "Tongs",
            "Pickaxes",
            "Trumpets"
          ],
          "answer": "Trumpets"
        },
        {
          "number": 43,
          "question": "What is the goblin name for Thorin's sword?",
          "options": [
            "Beater",
            "Biter",
            "Thunderbolt",
            "Murderer"
          ],
          "answer": "Biter"
        },
        {
          "number": 44,
          "question": "Who carries Bilbo at first as they try to escape from the mines after Gandalf kills the Great Goblin?",
          "options": [
            "Dori",
            "Dwalin",
            "Nori",
            "Ori"
          ],
          "answer": "Dori"
        },
        {
          "number": 45,
          "question": "What is obviously magical about Gandalf's sword Glamdring (Foe-hammer)?",
          "options": [
            "It burns blue when goblins are nearby",
            "It cannot be taken out of the owner's hand unless the owner is killed",
            "It becomes invisible when the owner is in danger",
            "It emits a high-pitched screeching sound when it kills goblins"
          ],
          "answer": "It burns blue when goblins are nearby"
        },
        {
          "number": 46,
          "question": "Who is carrying Bilbo when the goblins find them for the second time?",
          "options": [
            "Gloin",
            "Dori",
            "Bifur",
            "Bombur"
          ],
          "answer": "Bombur"
        },
        {
          "number": 47,
          "question": "What light are the adventurers using to guide them inside the tunnels in Chapter 4?",
          "options": [
            "A torch dropped by a goblin when Thorin killed one",
            "The magical glow on Gandalf's staff",
            "A strange green glow given off by Gandalf's smoke rings",
            "The magical light given off by Orcrist and Glamdring when goblins are nearby"
          ],
          "answer": "The magical glow on Gandalf's staff"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "chapter_number": 5,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 48,
          "question": "Why can't the dwarves hear the goblins coming?",
          "options": [
            "The dwarves are talking too loudly",
            "The echoes inside the caves are too confusing",
            "The goblins have made themselves invisible",
            "The goblins are wearing soft shoes"
          ],
          "answer": "The goblins are wearing soft shoes"
        },
        {
          "number": 49,
          "question": "Why do the goblins not find Bilbo after he is knocked unconscious?",
          "options": [
            "The are too busy looking at the dwarves and Gandalf",
            "They see him, but do not bother with him",
            "He is lying quietly in a dark corner",
            "They have all been killed by Gandalf's magic"
          ],
          "answer": "He is lying quietly in a dark corner"
        },
        {
          "number": 50,
          "question": "What does Bilbo find on the floor in Chapter 5?",
          "options": [
            "A ring",
            "A knife",
            "A slice of bacon",
            "His pipe and tobacco pouch"
          ],
          "answer": "A ring"
        },
        {
          "number": 51,
          "question": "What does Bilbo learn about his sword in Chapter 5?",
          "options": [
            "He can use it like a match to make fire",
            "It is an elvish blade like Glamdring and Orcrist",
            "It helps him see in the dark",
            "It acts as a compass so he does not lose his sense of direction"
          ],
          "answer": "It is an elvish blade like Glamdring and Orcrist"
        },
        {
          "number": 52,
          "question": "What animals does Bilbo sense as he wanders through the dark tunnels in Chapter 5?",
          "options": [
            "Snakes",
            "Fish",
            "None - the goblins have eaten everything alive",
            "Bats"
          ],
          "answer": "Bats"
        },
        {
          "number": 53,
          "question": "What stops Bilbo from going forward in the dark tunnels in Chapter 5?",
          "options": [
            "He hears goblins going fishing",
            "Gollum catches him",
            "He blunders into a dead end",
            "He comes to the edge of a subterranean lake"
          ],
          "answer": "He comes to the edge of a subterranean lake"
        },
        {
          "number": 54,
          "question": "How does Gollum get from his island to the shore of the lake?",
          "options": [
            "He paddles a little boat",
            "He rides on the back of blind fish",
            "His ring helps him walk across the surface of the water",
            "He swims, as he is an excellent swimmer"
          ],
          "answer": "He paddles a little boat"
        },
        {
          "number": 55,
          "question": "What does Gollum eat?",
          "options": [
            "Fish and goblins",
            "Fish and mushrooms",
            "Ponies and goblins",
            "Bats and spiders"
          ],
          "answer": "Fish and goblins"
        },
        {
          "number": 56,
          "question": "What is the answer to Bilbo's first riddle?",
          "options": [
            "Teeth",
            "A mountain",
            "The wind",
            "White horses"
          ],
          "answer": "Teeth"
        },
        {
          "number": 57,
          "question": "What will happen if Bilbo loses the riddle contest?",
          "options": [
            "Bilbo will become Gollum's slave",
            "He will have to give the ring back to Gollum",
            "Gollum will hand him over to the goblins in return for food",
            "Gollum will eat him"
          ],
          "answer": "Gollum will eat him"
        },
        {
          "number": 58,
          "question": "Where did Gollum live before coming to the underground lake?",
          "options": [
            "Nowhere - he has always lived on his island",
            "On the top of a windy mountain",
            "With his grandmother in a hole in a bank beside a river",
            "With the goblins, but he was banished after he ate one of them"
          ],
          "answer": "With his grandmother in a hole in a bank beside a river"
        },
        {
          "number": 59,
          "question": "What is \"never thirsty, ever drinking/All in mail never clinking?\"",
          "options": [
            "Gollum's grandmother",
            "A fish",
            "The skeleton of a drowned knight",
            "Goblins"
          ],
          "answer": "A fish"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "chapter_number": 6,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 60,
          "question": "What does Gollum call the ring?",
          "options": [
            "My precious",
            "My birthday present",
            "My hiding place",
            "My special secret"
          ],
          "answer": "My birthday present"
        },
        {
          "number": 61,
          "question": "Who does Bilbo see first after escaping Gollum and the dark tunnels?",
          "options": [
            "Bombur",
            "Gandalf",
            "Balin",
            "Gollum"
          ],
          "answer": "Balin"
        },
        {
          "number": 62,
          "question": "What does Bilbo not tell the dwarves about his adventures inside the tunnels?",
          "options": [
            "That his little sword is an elvish blade like Glamdring and Orcrist",
            "That he had pity on Gollum and did not kill him when he had the chance",
            "That he now has a ring that makes him invisible when he puts it on",
            "That Gollum wanted to eat him if he lost the riddle contest"
          ],
          "answer": "That he now has a ring that makes him invisible when he puts it on"
        },
        {
          "number": 63,
          "question": "What type of enchantments is Gandalf especially good at?",
          "options": [
            "Illusions and turning his enemies to stone",
            "Prophecy and pathfinding",
            "Fire and lights",
            "Calling down lightning and thunder"
          ],
          "answer": "Fire and lights"
        },
        {
          "number": 64,
          "question": "What day of the week was it when the adventurers were captured?",
          "options": [
            "Monday night (or Tuesday morning)",
            "Tuesday night (or Wednesday morning)",
            "Monday morning (or Sunday night)",
            "Thursday evening (or Thursday morning)"
          ],
          "answer": "Monday night (or Tuesday morning)"
        },
        {
          "number": 65,
          "question": "What does Bilbo find to eat as they walk through the woods in Chapter 6?",
          "options": [
            "Sorrel and wild strawberries",
            "Blackberries and strawberries",
            "Mushrooms and crab-apples",
            "Hawthorn berries and blackberries"
          ],
          "answer": "Sorrel and wild strawberries"
        },
        {
          "number": 66,
          "question": "Why is the magic ring unable to protect the wearer from the wargs?",
          "options": [
            "Wargs are magical, and the ring does not work on them",
            "Wargs can find the wearer by their sense of smell",
            "Wargs have especially keen hearing",
            "Wargs can still see the wearer's shadow, even by moonlight"
          ],
          "answer": "Wargs can find the wearer by their sense of smell"
        },
        {
          "number": 67,
          "question": "What sort of tree does Gandalf take refuge from the wargs in?",
          "options": [
            "An oak",
            "A spruce",
            "A pine",
            "A fir"
          ],
          "answer": "A pine"
        },
        {
          "number": 68,
          "question": "Why did the wargs come to the clearing where the adventurers were?",
          "options": [
            "The goblins had sent the wargs to hunt down the adventurers",
            "The wolves were running away from the woodsmen who had settled in the area",
            "They were going to meet the goblins so they could go raiding together",
            "The wargs could smell the adventurers and came to hunt them"
          ],
          "answer": "They were going to meet the goblins so they could go raiding together"
        },
        {
          "number": 69,
          "question": "What colors of flame does Gandalf use to drive the wolves back with?",
          "options": [
            "Blue, white and purple",
            "Blue, red and green",
            "Red, yellow and orange",
            "Green, black and white"
          ],
          "answer": "Blue, red and green"
        },
        {
          "number": 70,
          "question": "What first alerts the Lord of the Eagles to the events in the wood?",
          "options": [
            "The flames in the forest",
            "The howling of the wolves",
            "The line of goblin soldiers marching towards the forest",
            "A magical message from Gandalf"
          ],
          "answer": "The howling of the wolves"
        },
        {
          "number": 71,
          "question": "How does the forest catch on fire in Chapter 6?",
          "options": [
            "A dead tree is hit by summer lightning",
            "Gandalf lights the fire to attract the attention of the eagles",
            "The goblins light it deliberately to kill the adventurers",
            "The wargs spread it accidentally after Gandalf sets their coats alight"
          ],
          "answer": "The wargs spread it accidentally after Gandalf sets their coats alight"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "chapter_number": 7,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 72,
          "question": "What does Bilbo think the eagles will do to him at first?",
          "options": [
            "He thinks they will give him back to the goblins",
            "He is afraid they will drop him over the edge of their eyrie",
            "He thinks they plan to eat him",
            "He hopes that they will give him a meal"
          ],
          "answer": "He thinks they plan to eat him"
        },
        {
          "number": 73,
          "question": "What does Bilbo eat for breakfast when he wakes up in the eagles' eyrie?",
          "options": [
            "Bread and water",
            "Bacon and eggs",
            "Cold mutton and rabbit",
            "Cold ham and apples"
          ],
          "answer": "Cold mutton and rabbit"
        },
        {
          "number": 74,
          "question": "What reward do the dwarves give to the eagles at the end of the adventures?",
          "options": [
            "A golden crown for the Lord of Eagles and golden collars for his fifteen chieftans",
            "A wagon load of silver and gold",
            "Specially designed spurs of steel that will help them fight agains the goblins better",
            "A magnificent necklace set with rubies and emeralds"
          ],
          "answer": "A golden crown for the Lord of Eagles and golden collars for his fifteen chieftans"
        },
        {
          "number": 75,
          "question": "What special ability does Beorn have?",
          "options": [
            "He can hunt any animal alive with his bare hands",
            "He can change from a man into a black bear",
            "He can handle bees without being stung",
            "He can lift rocks as big as the Carrock"
          ],
          "answer": "He can change from a man into a black bear"
        },
        {
          "number": 76,
          "question": "Which dwarf has to come to Beorn's house alone?",
          "options": [
            "Bombur",
            "Thorin",
            "Dwalin",
            "Dori"
          ],
          "answer": "Bombur"
        },
        {
          "number": 77,
          "question": "What is Beorn doing when Gandalf and Bilbo arrive at his house?",
          "options": [
            "Chopping wood",
            "Extracting honey from his hives",
            "Shearing sheep",
            "Churning butter"
          ],
          "answer": "Chopping wood"
        },
        {
          "number": 78,
          "question": "What is the name of Gandalf's cousin?",
          "options": [
            "Radagast",
            "Saruman",
            "Elrond",
            "Mithrandir"
          ],
          "answer": "Radagast"
        },
        {
          "number": 79,
          "question": "What animals set up the dinner table and light the lamps in Beorn's hall?",
          "options": [
            "Bears, boars and oxen",
            "Bees, eagles and enslaved wolves",
            "Sheep, cattle and cats",
            "Ponies, dogs and sheep"
          ],
          "answer": "Ponies, dogs and sheep"
        },
        {
          "number": 80,
          "question": "How does Beorn react to the dwarves' talk of gold, silver and jewels?",
          "options": [
            "He is amazed at the skill the dwarves talk about",
            "He ignores them, as he has no interest in treasures",
            "He is angry and perplexed at their greed",
            "He is intrigued and starts becoming greedy for a share of the treasure"
          ],
          "answer": "He ignores them, as he has no interest in treasures"
        },
        {
          "number": 81,
          "question": "What happened outside Beorn's hall on the first night the adventurers stayed there?",
          "options": [
            "Beorn and other bears held a meeting and a dance",
            "Beorn and Gandalf talked all night on top of the Carrock",
            "Beorn had a great battle against a pack of Wargs",
            "Beorn, in bear-shape, tried to kill the adventurers"
          ],
          "answer": "Beorn and other bears held a meeting and a dance"
        },
        {
          "number": 82,
          "question": "How does Beorn find out that Gandalf's story is true?",
          "options": [
            "His bees bring him the news",
            "The Lord of the Eagles tells him",
            "He finds the burnt wolf-glade and also forces a captive warg and goblin to tell him",
            "He finds the dead body of the Great Goblin"
          ],
          "answer": "He finds the burnt wolf-glade and also forces a captive warg and goblin to tell him"
        },
        {
          "number": 83,
          "question": "What does Bilbo see at nightfall as they travel towards Mirkwood?",
          "options": [
            "Wargs and goblins trying to sneak past Beorn's borders",
            "The borrowed ponies trying to escape",
            "Spies and servants of the Necromancer",
            "A great black bear (Beorn in his animal shape) following them"
          ],
          "answer": "A great black bear (Beorn in his animal shape) following them"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "chapter_number": 8,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 84,
          "question": "What is Gandalf's last piece of advice before he leaves the dwarves and Bilbo?",
          "options": [
            "Don't go near the Necromancer's tower",
            "You must either go through or give up the quest",
            "Keep going straight ahead, no matter what happens",
            "Don't leave the path"
          ],
          "answer": "Don't leave the path"
        },
        {
          "number": 85,
          "question": "What animals do the adventurers see quite frequently in the early stages of their journey through Mirkwood?",
          "options": [
            "Deer",
            "Black squirrels",
            "Poisonous snakes",
            "Wild boars"
          ],
          "answer": "Black squirrels"
        },
        {
          "number": 86,
          "question": "Why don't the adventurers drink from the black stream in the middle of Mirkwood?",
          "options": [
            "Beorn had warned them that the water was enchanted",
            "It looks poisonous and unhealthy",
            "They are more interested in getting across it",
            "It flows too fast to be safe if they stand on the brink and try to fill their waterskins"
          ],
          "answer": "Beorn had warned them that the water was enchanted"
        },
        {
          "number": 87,
          "question": "Who is supposed to ride in the boat with Bombur?",
          "options": [
            "Bofur",
            "Dwalin",
            "Bilbo",
            "Kili"
          ],
          "answer": "Dwalin"
        },
        {
          "number": 88,
          "question": "Why does Bombur fall into the enchanted river?",
          "options": [
            "Dwalin knocks him in accidentally",
            "The boat starts floating downstream so he jumps into the water",
            "A deer knocks him in",
            "He is too fat and clumsy to jump out of the boat without stumbling"
          ],
          "answer": "A deer knocks him in"
        },
        {
          "number": 89,
          "question": "Which of the following is not a change that the adventurers notice after encountering the hunt and the white deer?",
          "options": [
            "They begin to hear singing and laughter in the distance",
            "They start to see and hear birds in the branches above them",
            "They see autumn leaves beginning to fall from the trees",
            "The shadows in the forest do not seem as deep or dark"
          ],
          "answer": "They start to see and hear birds in the branches above them"
        },
        {
          "number": 90,
          "question": "What small creatures does Bilbo find at the top of the oak tree in Chapter 8?",
          "options": [
            "Centipedes and earwigs",
            "Squirrels and sparrows",
            "Black butterflies and spiders",
            "Moths and caterpillars"
          ],
          "answer": "Black butterflies and spiders"
        },
        {
          "number": 91,
          "question": "Who is the first to see the lights from the elves' feast?",
          "options": [
            "Bilbo",
            "Balin",
            "Thorin",
            "Bombur"
          ],
          "answer": "Balin"
        },
        {
          "number": 92,
          "question": "Which of the following does not happen when one of the adventurers steps into the ring of lights surrounding the elves' feast?",
          "options": [
            "The lights magically go out",
            "The elves begin singing an eerie tune",
            "The fire erupts in a shower of sparks",
            "The adventurers become confused and disoriented"
          ],
          "answer": "The elves begin singing an eerie tune"
        },
        {
          "number": 93,
          "question": "What wakes Bilbo up from his sleep after he realizes he is alone in Chapter 8, after coming across the elves' feast?",
          "options": [
            "A spider, which is trying to wrap him up in sticky thread",
            "A high-pitched buzzing noise made by a fly attempting to escape from the spiders",
            "The hunting horn of the elf king",
            "The shouts and cries of the dwarves"
          ],
          "answer": "A spider, which is trying to wrap him up in sticky thread"
        },
        {
          "number": 94,
          "question": "How does Bilbo kill the spiders who have captured the dwarves in their webs?",
          "options": [
            "He stabs them stealthily with Sting",
            "He enrages them so much that they fall out of their trees to their deaths",
            "He uses strands of their own webs to make nooses and strangles them",
            "He throws stones at them"
          ],
          "answer": "He throws stones at them"
        },
        {
          "number": 95,
          "question": "After they have defeated the spiders, who do the adventurers discover is missing?",
          "options": [
            "Bombur",
            "Thorin",
            "Dwalin",
            "Kili"
          ],
          "answer": "Thorin"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "chapter_number": 9,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 96,
          "question": "What sort of elves have taken Thorin prisoner?",
          "options": [
            "Sea Elves",
            "Light Elves",
            "Deep Elves",
            "Wood Elves"
          ],
          "answer": "Wood Elves"
        },
        {
          "number": 97,
          "question": "What weapons do the Wood Elves use when they take the dwarves prisoner?",
          "options": [
            "Bows and spears",
            "Swords and daggers",
            "Whips and clubs",
            "They freeze the dwarves with their magical powers"
          ],
          "answer": "Bows and spears"
        },
        {
          "number": 98,
          "question": "What is the Elf King's crown made of during autumn (fall)?",
          "options": [
            "Berries and red leaves",
            "Silver and white gems",
            "Gold and emeralds",
            "Oak leaves and acorns"
          ],
          "answer": "Berries and red leaves"
        },
        {
          "number": 99,
          "question": "Why are the dwarves glad to be captured by the elves (at first)?",
          "options": [
            "They are starving, and the elves will give their prisoners food",
            "They guess that the elves have taken Thorin prisoner and they want to be reunited with him",
            "The elves have been friends with the dwarves for hundreds of years",
            "They know that if they promise the elves a share of their treasure, they will be set free"
          ],
          "answer": "They are starving, and the elves will give their prisoners food"
        },
        {
          "number": 100,
          "question": "What question of Balin's enraged the Elvenking?",
          "options": [
            "Balin asks the Elvenking for food and drink before being set free",
            "Balin asks if the elves know anything about Smaug's treasure",
            "Balin asks if the spiders are the elves' pets",
            "Balin asks what has happened to Thorin"
          ],
          "answer": "Balin asks if the spiders are the elves' pets"
        },
        {
          "number": 101,
          "question": "How does Bilbo find food while skulking around in the Elvenking's palace?",
          "options": [
            "He takes it out of the barrels sent to Esgaroth",
            "He scrounges it off the rubbish heaps of the elves",
            "He steals it from the stores or the table when nobody is looking",
            "He slips out through the magic gates and goes hunting"
          ],
          "answer": "He steals it from the stores or the table when nobody is looking"
        },
        {
          "number": 102,
          "question": "What is mostly transported by river inside the barrels from the people of Laketown to the Wood Elves?",
          "options": [
            "Cider",
            "Mead",
            "Wine",
            "Ale"
          ],
          "answer": "Wine"
        },
        {
          "number": 103,
          "question": "In Chapter 9, with whom does the chief guard get drunk?",
          "options": [
            "The Elf King",
            "The king's butler",
            "The men who guided the barrels up the river",
            "The other guards"
          ],
          "answer": "The king's butler"
        },
        {
          "number": 104,
          "question": "What is the name of the elvenking's butler?",
          "options": [
            "Galion",
            "Legolas",
            "Dorwinion",
            "Thranduil"
          ],
          "answer": "Galion"
        },
        {
          "number": 105,
          "question": "What is the weak point in Bilbo's plan of escape from the elves?",
          "options": [
            "He forgot that the elves would notice that the barrels were still full",
            "He forgot to leave air-holes so the dwarves could breathe through",
            "He forgot that he had nobody to pack him inside a barrel",
            "He forgot that he couldn't swim"
          ],
          "answer": "He forgot that he had nobody to pack him inside a barrel"
        },
        {
          "number": 106,
          "question": "What nearly gives Bilbo's presence away to the men steering the barrels in spite of the invisibility conferred on him by the ring?",
          "options": [
            "His wet footprints and his sneezing",
            "His shadow in the torchlight",
            "He bumps into the men quite frequently",
            "His weight presses the barrels lower in the water"
          ],
          "answer": "His wet footprints and his sneezing"
        },
        {
          "number": 107,
          "question": "What is Thorin considering doing when he learns that the other dwarves are also in prison with him?",
          "options": [
            "Promising the Elvenking a share of the treasure",
            "Swearing to become a slave of the elves for the rest of his life",
            "Telling the Elvenking about the quest and the treasure",
            "Committing suicide"
          ],
          "answer": "Telling the Elvenking about the quest and the treasure"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "chapter_number": 10,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 108,
          "question": "What prediction of Gandalf's comes true in Chapter 9?",
          "options": [
            "The dwarves have learned to trust Bilbo to save them",
            "They will have to abandon their quest and return to digging coal",
            "They came to disaster when they left the path in Mirkwood",
            "They will be unable to reach the Lonely Mountain by Durin's Day"
          ],
          "answer": "The dwarves have learned to trust Bilbo to save them"
        },
        {
          "number": 109,
          "question": "What is the first landmark feature that Bilbo notices as the barrel he is riding takes him out of the forest?",
          "options": [
            "The Iron Hills to the northeast of the lake",
            "A landslide",
            "The Lonely Mountain",
            "The Long Lake"
          ],
          "answer": "The Lonely Mountain"
        },
        {
          "number": 110,
          "question": "What is the most common building material used in Laketown?",
          "options": [
            "Stone",
            "Wood",
            "Rammed earth",
            "Iron"
          ],
          "answer": "Wood"
        },
        {
          "number": 111,
          "question": "What had Fili's barrel been used to carry before he escaped inside it?",
          "options": [
            "Butter",
            "Wine",
            "Apples",
            "Cheese"
          ],
          "answer": "Apples"
        },
        {
          "number": 112,
          "question": "How does Bilbo manage to recognize Thorin after freeing him from the barrel?",
          "options": [
            "By his red cloak, black boots and dark green tunic",
            "By his blue hood with the silver tassel and by his golden chain",
            "By a distinctive scar left from his encounter with Smaug in the distant past",
            "By his long nose and bristling beard"
          ],
          "answer": "By his blue hood with the silver tassel and by his golden chain"
        },
        {
          "number": 113,
          "question": "What happened to Thorin's sword Orcrist?",
          "options": [
            "It had fallen off and become lost while the Eagles were rescuing the adventurers from the wargs and goblins",
            "Nothing - Thorin uses it to enhance his kingly apperance when he presents himself to the Master of Laketown",
            "The King of the Wood Elves took it from Thorin when he was made prisoner",
            "It had become hopelessly rusty in the trip down the river"
          ],
          "answer": "The King of the Wood Elves took it from Thorin when he was made prisoner"
        },
        {
          "number": 114,
          "question": "What skills or interests does the Master have that have made him the ruler of Laketown?",
          "options": [
            "His excellent memory and people skills",
            "His economic expertise",
            "His love of old songs",
            "His knowledge of the Elvish languages"
          ],
          "answer": "His economic expertise"
        },
        {
          "number": 115,
          "question": "Why is the King of the Wood Elves wiser than the men of Laketown?",
          "options": [
            "He knows a way to kill Smaug that the Lake-men do not",
            "He realizes that the dwarves will have to steal from Smaug rather than attempt to kill him, which is what the Lake-men believe",
            "He believes in the old songs and tales that the Master of Laketown has forgotten about",
            "He quickly realizes how the dwarves managed to escape from his dungeons"
          ],
          "answer": "He realizes that the dwarves will have to steal from Smaug rather than attempt to kill him, which is what the Lake-men believe"
        },
        {
          "number": 116,
          "question": "Why is Bilbo unhappy during their stay in Laketown?",
          "options": [
            "He is suspicious about the possible motives of the Master",
            "He has a bad cold",
            "He does not like the food that the Lake-men offer them",
            "He still wishes he was back in his hobbit-hole"
          ],
          "answer": "He has a bad cold"
        },
        {
          "number": 117,
          "question": "What does the Master believe about Thorin and his company at first?",
          "options": [
            "That Thorin will be killed by the dragon",
            "That Thorin is the true King Under the Mountain",
            "That Thorin will be a worthy ally and trade partner",
            "That they are frauds"
          ],
          "answer": "That they are frauds"
        },
        {
          "number": 118,
          "question": "How long do the dwarves and Bilbo stay in Laketown?",
          "options": [
            "We are not told",
            "A fortnight",
            "Two days",
            "Three weeks"
          ],
          "answer": "A fortnight"
        },
        {
          "number": 119,
          "question": "Who sit beside Thorin at the high table after Thorin proclaims himself as the descendant of Thror, King Under the Mountain?",
          "options": [
            "Bofur and Bombur",
            "Dwalin and Balin",
            "Bilbo and the Master",
            "Fili and Kili"
          ],
          "answer": "Fili and Kili"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "chapter_number": 11,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 120,
          "question": "What mistaken belief is held by the younger people of Laketown?",
          "options": [
            "They believe that the dragon is harmless and even friendly",
            "They believe that Thorin is not the rightful King Under the Mountain",
            "They believe that the river will flow with gold once the King Under the Mountain returns",
            "They believe that the dragon does not exist"
          ],
          "answer": "They believe that the dragon does not exist"
        },
        {
          "number": 121,
          "question": "What is the name of the hill close to where the dwarves and Bilbo make their first camp approaching the Lonely Mountain?",
          "options": [
            "Dale",
            "Ravenhill",
            "Dragonmount",
            "Ravensdown"
          ],
          "answer": "Ravenhill"
        },
        {
          "number": 122,
          "question": "What type of birds inhabit the area of the mountain and valleys closest to the Front Gate?",
          "options": [
            "None - the dragon has eaten them all",
            "Thrushes",
            "Crows",
            "Ravens"
          ],
          "answer": "Crows"
        },
        {
          "number": 123,
          "question": "What does Bilbo deduce from seeing the smoke and steam issuing from the Front Gate?",
          "options": [
            "That the dragon is alive",
            "That the dragon has set himself on fire",
            "That the dragon is getting ready to come out and eat them",
            "That the dragon is watching them from the side of the mountain"
          ],
          "answer": "That the dragon is alive"
        },
        {
          "number": 124,
          "question": "Who finds the 'doorstep' of the secret door in Chapter 11?",
          "options": [
            "Thorin, Bilbo and Balin",
            "Nori, Dori and Ori",
            "Bilbo, Fili and Kili",
            "Bifur, Bofur and Bombur"
          ],
          "answer": "Bilbo, Fili and Kili"
        },
        {
          "number": 125,
          "question": "How can the dwarves and Bilbo reach the third camp outside the 'doorstep'?",
          "options": [
            "Either by a narrow path along the edge of a precipice or by ropes",
            "Only by ropes - no other way is possible",
            "By floating along the river",
            "On horseback"
          ],
          "answer": "Either by a narrow path along the edge of a precipice or by ropes"
        },
        {
          "number": 126,
          "question": "What phase of the moon is showing when Bilbo realizes that Durin's Day has come and they can find the keyhole?",
          "options": [
            "A half moon",
            "A new moon",
            "A full moon",
            "A waning crescent"
          ],
          "answer": "A new moon"
        },
        {
          "number": 127,
          "question": "How high is the doorway that leads into the secret tunnel in Chapter 11?",
          "options": [
            "Five feet high",
            "We are not told",
            "Three feet high",
            "Six feet high"
          ],
          "answer": "Five feet high"
        },
        {
          "number": 128,
          "question": "Which dwarf is not present on the Doorstep when the door is finally opened?",
          "options": [
            "Balin",
            "Bombur",
            "Thorin",
            "Gloin"
          ],
          "answer": "Bombur"
        },
        {
          "number": 129,
          "question": "Which of the following methods do the dwarves not use in an attempt to open the secret door before the keyhole is revealed?",
          "options": [
            "Throwing loose rocks at the cliff face",
            "Beating on the stone and pushing at the cliff face",
            "Using pickaxes to break through the stone",
            "Reciting spells that can open locked doors"
          ],
          "answer": "Throwing loose rocks at the cliff face"
        },
        {
          "number": 130,
          "question": "What animals or creatures can be found near the doorstep?",
          "options": [
            "Thrushes and giant snails",
            "Thrushes and ravens",
            "Snails and scorpions",
            "Snakes, spiders and crows"
          ],
          "answer": "Thrushes and giant snails"
        },
        {
          "number": 131,
          "question": "What do the dwarves suggest that Bilbo should do when they begin to despair of being able to open the secret door in Chapter 11?",
          "options": [
            "Go back to Laketown and ask for more supplies and weapons",
            "Try to capture one of the thrushes, crows or ravens and use its feathers as a disguise to sneak into the mountain through the Front Gate",
            "Go into the mountain through the Front Gate using his magic ring",
            "Talk to the thrushes and see if they know the secret of opening the door"
          ],
          "answer": "Go into the mountain through the Front Gate using his magic ring"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "chapter_number": 12,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 132,
          "question": "Why does Bombur choose to stay below and guard the ponies in Chapter 11?",
          "options": [
            "He lost a bet and had to go on guard duty as a result",
            "He thinks he is too fat for the ropes and that he will get dizzy or trip on the path",
            "He does not believe that Bilbo and the others have really found the secret door",
            "He is very fond of the ponies and doesn't want to leave them behind"
          ],
          "answer": "He thinks he is too fat for the ropes and that he will get dizzy or trip on the path"
        },
        {
          "number": 133,
          "question": "In Chapter 12, who volunteers to come some of the way down the tunnel with Bilbo?",
          "options": [
            "Fili",
            "Thorin",
            "Balin",
            "Kili"
          ],
          "answer": "Balin"
        },
        {
          "number": 134,
          "question": "What is the first hint of the dragon's presence that Bilbo notices as he descends the tunnel?",
          "options": [
            "Wisps of smoke",
            "The rumbling sound of Smaug's breathing or snoring",
            "The air about him grows hotter",
            "A reddish glow"
          ],
          "answer": "A reddish glow"
        },
        {
          "number": 135,
          "question": "What colors is Smaug?",
          "options": [
            "Red and gold",
            "Red and green",
            "Red and black",
            "Green and gold"
          ],
          "answer": "Red and gold"
        },
        {
          "number": 136,
          "question": "What does Bilbo manage to steal from Smaug in Chapter 12?",
          "options": [
            "A sharp sword",
            "A golden cup",
            "A pocketful of gold coins",
            "A necklace of rubies"
          ],
          "answer": "A golden cup"
        },
        {
          "number": 137,
          "question": "What did Smaug meet in his nightmare before he wakes up?",
          "options": [
            "A brave warrior with a sword",
            "An army of archers",
            "A bigger, stronger dragon wanting to steal his hoard",
            "Thieves stealing from his hoard"
          ],
          "answer": "A brave warrior with a sword"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "chapter_number": 13,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 138,
          "question": "Why does Smaug react with such great fury in Chapter 12?",
          "options": [
            "He smells the dwarves and realizes that they are coming to kill him",
            "He is hungry after his long sleep and his hunger infuriates him",
            "He is extremely disturbed by his nightmare",
            "He is outraged that someone has dared to steal from him"
          ],
          "answer": "He is outraged that someone has dared to steal from him"
        },
        {
          "number": 139,
          "question": "How does Bilbo know that the gem he stumbles across is the Arkenstone?",
          "options": [
            "He does not know it is the Arkenstone at all and fails to recognize it",
            "Bilbo recognizes it from Thorin's description",
            "He hears the ghost of a long-dead dwarf whisper its name to him as he picks it up",
            "It is written in letters of gold across one of the facets of the stone"
          ],
          "answer": "Bilbo recognizes it from Thorin's description"
        },
        {
          "number": 140,
          "question": "What makes Bilbo drop his torch after finding the Arkenstone?",
          "options": [
            "He trips over a necklace of pearls",
            "He is so surprised when he sees the Arkenstone that he drops the torch",
            "He believes the dragon is coming back and wants to hide",
            "A bat startles him"
          ],
          "answer": "A bat startles him"
        },
        {
          "number": 141,
          "question": "What does Thorin take as armor and weapons from the hoard of Smaug's treasure?",
          "options": [
            "A coat of silver mail, a helmet encrusted with diamonds and an ivory bow",
            "Silver armour, a belt set with rubies and a black mace set with diamonds",
            "A coat of gold-plated rings, an axe with a silver haft and a belt encrusted with scarlet stones",
            "Spears with the heads inlaid with gold, an emerald-studded shield and a crown"
          ],
          "answer": "A coat of gold-plated rings, an axe with a silver haft and a belt encrusted with scarlet stones"
        },
        {
          "number": 142,
          "question": "For whom was the armor Bilbo is rewarded with in Chapter 13 originally made?",
          "options": [
            "Thorin when he was younger",
            "The bride of the King Under the Mountain",
            "A young elf prince",
            "Bullroarer Took as a reward for killing the goblin chieftain"
          ],
          "answer": "A young elf prince"
        },
        {
          "number": 143,
          "question": "Apart from the dragon, what other animals live inside the Lonely Mountain?",
          "options": [
            "Nothing",
            "Bats",
            "Spiders",
            "Snails"
          ],
          "answer": "Bats"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "chapter_number": 14,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 144,
          "question": "Who makes the cram that the dwarves and Bilbo eat while camping at Ravenhill?",
          "options": [
            "The dwarves, using an ancient and secret recipe",
            "The Wood Elves",
            "Beorn",
            "The Lake-men"
          ],
          "answer": "The Lake-men"
        },
        {
          "number": 145,
          "question": "What is the full name of the grim-faced man who habitually predicts disasters like floods and poisoned fish?",
          "options": [
            "Bowman the Bard",
            "Bard ap Girion",
            "Bard the Bowman",
            "Bard of Esgaroth"
          ],
          "answer": "Bard the Bowman"
        },
        {
          "number": 146,
          "question": "Why do the people of Lake-town destroy the bridges as a defense against the onslaught of the dragon?",
          "options": [
            "The Master ordered them to do so in the hopes that his rival, Bard, would be killed",
            "The bridges are the only part of the town that is vulnerable to dragon-fire",
            "The dragon can then only attack them from the air (which makes him vulnerable to arrows) or have his fire quenched by the cold water of the lake",
            "They are attempting to fool the dragon into thinking they have left the town"
          ],
          "answer": "The dragon can then only attack them from the air (which makes him vulnerable to arrows) or have his fire quenched by the cold water of the lake"
        },
        {
          "number": 147,
          "question": "Why do most of the arrows shot at Smaug have no effect on him?",
          "options": [
            "Smag has a magic of his own that makes him invulnerable",
            "The arrows either bounce off his scales and diamond encrusted underbelly, or he incinerates them with his fiery breath",
            "The wind from Smaug's wings makes all the arrows miss their targets",
            "Smaug flies so high and fast that no arrows can reach him"
          ],
          "answer": "The arrows either bounce off his scales and diamond encrusted underbelly, or he incinerates them with his fiery breath"
        },
        {
          "number": 148,
          "question": "Why is Bard astonished when the thrush lands on his shoulder?",
          "options": [
            "He believes the thrush is a spy of the dragon's sent to distract his aim",
            "He thought all the thrushes in the area had been killed by the dragon",
            "He can understand its speech",
            "The thrush is the emblem on his family coat of arms"
          ],
          "answer": "He can understand its speech"
        },
        {
          "number": 149,
          "question": "Why can Bard understand the speech of the thrush?",
          "options": [
            "It was a special, magical thrush that could make any human that spoke to it understand",
            "His ancestors came from Dale, where the people had the power of understanding the speech of birds",
            "The thrush spoke Bard's native language",
            "He has studied the language of birds and is used to it"
          ],
          "answer": "His ancestors came from Dale, where the people had the power of understanding the speech of birds"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "chapter_number": 15,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 150,
          "question": "In Chapter 14, qho does Bard ask for help in making sure that the refugees from Laketown have food and shelter to help them through the oncoming winter?",
          "options": [
            "Beorn and the woodsmen who hunt the Wargs",
            "The King of the Wood Elves",
            "The goblins of the Misty Mountains",
            "The dwarves of the Iron Hills"
          ],
          "answer": "The King of the Wood Elves"
        },
        {
          "number": 151,
          "question": "What type of bird brings Bilbo and the dwarves the news of the dragon's death?",
          "options": [
            "A thrush",
            "An eagle",
            "A raven",
            "A crow"
          ],
          "answer": "A raven"
        },
        {
          "number": 152,
          "question": "How old is Roac the raven?",
          "options": [
            "300",
            "We are not told",
            "153",
            "135"
          ],
          "answer": "153"
        },
        {
          "number": 153,
          "question": "What advice does Roac give to Thorin about the Lakemen?",
          "options": [
            "To trust all of them, especially the Master",
            "To trust Bard, and to share the treasure with them",
            "Not to trust any of them, as they want to steal the gold",
            "To attack first before the elf army arrives"
          ],
          "answer": "To trust Bard, and to share the treasure with them"
        },
        {
          "number": 154,
          "question": "What does Bilbo most want to happen while the dwarves are preparing for a siege by the elves and Lakemen?",
          "options": [
            "He wants to steal away with his share of the treasure and leave the dwarves to fight the Lakemen over the rest",
            "He wants the armies to go away and leave them alone",
            "He wants a peaceful resolution to the situation - and enough food",
            "He wants Gandalf to turn up and take him back to his hobbit hole again"
          ],
          "answer": "He wants a peaceful resolution to the situation - and enough food"
        },
        {
          "number": 155,
          "question": "How do the dwarves manage to obtain three ponies in Chapter 15?",
          "options": [
            "Bilbo steals the ponies off the Lakemen using his magic ring",
            "Dain from the Iron Hills sends the ponies to help Thorin",
            "They capture and tame wild ponies that were living in the area",
            "They find that three of the ponies escaped from the dragon and were wandering down the river"
          ],
          "answer": "They find that three of the ponies escaped from the dragon and were wandering down the river"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "chapter_number": 16,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 156,
          "question": "Which of the following does Bard not use as a reason why the dwarves should share the treasure with the people of Laketown?",
          "options": [
            "Some of the treasure came from Dale and belonged to Bard's ancestors",
            "The dragon had a lot of treasure, so there is plenty for all to share",
            "Bard was the one who actually killed the dragon",
            "The people of Laketown helped the dwarves when the dwarves were in need, but are now in need themselves"
          ],
          "answer": "The dragon had a lot of treasure, so there is plenty for all to share"
        },
        {
          "number": 157,
          "question": "Who is supposed to be on watch when Bilbo steals out of the stronghold to the elves and Lakemen?",
          "options": [
            "Bombur",
            "Thorin",
            "Kili",
            "Dwalin"
          ],
          "answer": "Bombur"
        },
        {
          "number": 158,
          "question": "In Chapter 16, who does Bilbo deal with and offer his share of the treasure to, along with the Arkenstone?",
          "options": [
            "Bard and the King of the Wood Elves",
            "Gandalf and Bard",
            "Bard and the Master",
            "The Elvish High Council"
          ],
          "answer": "Bard and the King of the Wood Elves"
        },
        {
          "number": 159,
          "question": "What unexpected news does Bilbo give the elves and Lakemen?",
          "options": [
            "Dain from the Iron Hills is coming to Thorin's aid",
            "Thorin is weakening and is prepared to share",
            "Smaug had a mate who is still alive inside the mountain",
            "The goblins are on their way to take the treasure"
          ],
          "answer": "Dain from the Iron Hills is coming to Thorin's aid"
        },
        {
          "number": 160,
          "question": "How does the Elvenking react to the sight of the Arkenstone?",
          "options": [
            "He is consumed by lust for the gem and is willing to renounce the rest of the treasure if he can have the Arkenstone",
            "He rejects Bilbo's offer as treacherous and ignoble, preferring instead to fight fairly for a share of the treasure",
            "He is amazed by its beauty and questions Bilbo's right to give it to him",
            "He is unimpressed by it"
          ],
          "answer": "He is amazed by its beauty and questions Bilbo's right to give it to him"
        },
        {
          "number": 161,
          "question": "Who does Bilbo meet unexpectedly in the camp of the elves and Lakemen?",
          "options": [
            "Gandalf",
            "Thorin",
            "Gollum",
            "Beorn.,"
          ],
          "answer": "Gandalf"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "chapter_number": 17,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 162,
          "question": "What is the other name for the Arkenstone?",
          "options": [
            "The Heart of the Mountain",
            "The Heart of Darkness",
            "The Heart of the Dragon",
            "The Mountain of Light"
          ],
          "answer": "The Heart of the Mountain"
        },
        {
          "number": 163,
          "question": "How does Thorin learn that Bilbo was the one who gave the Arkenstone to Bard and the Elvenking?",
          "options": [
            "A raven who saw Bilbo going to the camp tells him",
            "Bard tells Thorin where he got the Arkenstone from",
            "Bilbo confesses to giving it to them",
            "Thorin finds Bilbo's distinctive footprints leading out of the stronghold"
          ],
          "answer": "Bilbo confesses to giving it to them"
        },
        {
          "number": 164,
          "question": "Who carries the wooden casket holding the Arkenstone to the parley with Thorin?",
          "options": [
            "An unnamed wood-elf",
            "Bard the Bowman",
            "The Master of Laketown",
            "Gandalf"
          ],
          "answer": "Gandalf"
        },
        {
          "number": 165,
          "question": "Which of the following does Thorin not threaten to do to Bilbo in Chapter 17?",
          "options": [
            "Throw him off the cliff",
            "Never be friends with him again",
            "Shoot at his feet with arrows",
            "Stab him with his own elvish dagger"
          ],
          "answer": "Stab him with his own elvish dagger"
        },
        {
          "number": 166,
          "question": "What do the dwarves of the Iron Hills wear that is their special technological secret?",
          "options": [
            "Seven-league boots that help them cover long distances quickly",
            "Knee-length hauberks of stainless steel",
            "Helmets made of mithril",
            "Flexible mail trousers or hose"
          ],
          "answer": "Flexible mail trousers or hose"
        },
        {
          "number": 167,
          "question": "What is the name of Dain's father?",
          "options": [
            "Thrain",
            "Carc",
            "Nain",
            "Thorin"
          ],
          "answer": "Nain"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "chapter_number": 18,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 168,
          "question": "Who attacks first and starts the war over the dragon gold?",
          "options": [
            "The goblins and wargs",
            "The dwarves",
            "The elves",
            "The Lakemen"
          ],
          "answer": "The dwarves"
        },
        {
          "number": 169,
          "question": "What wound has Gandalf sustained during the Battle of the Five Armies?",
          "options": [
            "Loss of half a foot when a goblin hacked it off with an axe",
            "A bad cut to the head that required stitching",
            "A broken arm from falling off a cliff",
            "An undefined wound in the arm that requires him to wear a sling"
          ],
          "answer": "An undefined wound in the arm that requires him to wear a sling"
        },
        {
          "number": 170,
          "question": "Which dwarves are killed in the battle or die because of wounds sustained during it?",
          "options": [
            "Dori, Nori and Ori",
            "Bifur, Bofur and Bombur",
            "Thorin, Fili and Kili",
            "Thorin, Balin and Dwalin"
          ],
          "answer": "Thorin, Fili and Kili"
        },
        {
          "number": 171,
          "question": "Who killed Bolg, the goblin cheiftan?",
          "options": [
            "Beorn in bear's shape",
            "Gandalf, who called down lightning",
            "Bard the Bowman",
            "Thorin, who got his death-wound fighting single-handed against Bolg"
          ],
          "answer": "Beorn in bear's shape"
        },
        {
          "number": 172,
          "question": "What treasures are placed on Thorin's body and/or tomb when he is buried?",
          "options": [
            "The shield and sword he carried in his last battle",
            "The Arkenstone and the sword Orcrist",
            "A golden statue of Smaug",
            "The crown that had been his grandfather's"
          ],
          "answer": "The Arkenstone and the sword Orcrist"
        },
        {
          "number": 173,
          "question": "What gift does Bard the Bowman give to the Elvenking?",
          "options": [
            "A chest full of diamonds",
            "The rubies that had belonged to Bard's ancestors",
            "All the crowns that could be found in Smaug's treasure",
            "The emeralds that had belonged to King Girion of Dale"
          ],
          "answer": "The emeralds that had belonged to King Girion of Dale"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "chapter_number": 19,
      "multiple_choice": [
        {
          "number": 174,
          "question": "What does Bilbo give to the Elvenking to pay for the food and wine he stole from him?",
          "options": [
            "A necklace of silver and pearls",
            "A chest of gold",
            "His sword Sting",
            "A crown of silver set with diamonds"
          ],
          "answer": "A necklace of silver and pearls"
        },
        {
          "number": 175,
          "question": "Where are Bilbo and Gandalf when Bilbo learns what Gandalf was doing while they were in Mirkwood?",
          "options": [
            "Going over the mountain road in the Misty Mountains",
            "At Beorn's house",
            "At the palace of the King of the Wood Elves",
            "In Rivendell"
          ],
          "answer": "In Rivendell"
        },
        {
          "number": 176,
          "question": "What wakes Bilbo while he is sleeping at Rivendell in Chapter 19?",
          "options": [
            "Gandalf and Elrond talking over their adventures",
            "Elves singing outside his window",
            "The snoring of a captive goblin",
            "An alarm warning them of an attack by bandits"
          ],
          "answer": "Elves singing outside his window"
        },
        {
          "number": 177,
          "question": "How long do Gandalf and Bilbo stay at Rivendell on the return journey?",
          "options": [
            "A month",
            "A fortnight",
            "A week",
            "We are not told"
          ],
          "answer": "A week"
        },
        {
          "number": 178,
          "question": "Where else does Bilbo get treasure from, apart from his share of Smaug's hoard?",
          "options": [
            "A gift from Beorn",
            "A gift from Elrond",
            "The troll's treasure",
            "He steals some from the goblins"
          ],
          "answer": "The troll's treasure"
        },
        {
          "number": 179,
          "question": "Who are the auctioneers selling off Bilbo's house and effects?",
          "options": [
            "The Hobbiton Historic Places Trust",
            "Mr. Sackville-Baggins and Company",
            "Messrs Grubb, Grubb and Burrowes",
            "Messrs Burrowes, Took and Grubb"
          ],
          "answer": "Messrs Grubb, Grubb and Burrowes"
        },
        {
          "number": 180,
          "question": "On what date was the auction of Bilbo's house and effects to take place?",
          "options": [
            "The 12 of June",
            "The 4th of July",
            "The 22nd of June",
            "The first of May"
          ],
          "answer": "The 22nd of June"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}